# MOHSEN ESMAEILI NodeJS Backend Developer

Email: m-esm@hotmail.com

Tel: +98 912 891 7370

GitHub: github.com/m-esm

LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/m-esm

## PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

I consider myself a futuristic, self-educated and experienced NodeJS developer, I've started my career as a web developer back in 2012 and working as a NodeJS backend engineer since 2016. I currently focus on creating scalable backend services. Recently started creating applications using AI/ML services on the cloud. Some topics I've worked on in recent years include:

- Typescript, NestJS, Fastify, ExpressJS, Koa, Hapi
- MongoDB, Mongoose, Redis, RabbitMQ
- MSSql, PostgreSQL, MySql, RealtimeDB
- Experience with TDD, DDD
- Experience with Docker, CI/CD
- Machine Learning, Encryption, Google Cloud Services, AWS

## **EMPLOYMENT HISTORY**

Aug, 2020 - Feb, 2021

BoomFit - Melbourne, Australia

NodeJS Backend Developer - Full-time Contract

Boomfit application is a marketplace for fitness workout videos. I'm working closely with the client team to deliver REST API features while scaling the backend services for streaming, data processing and video intelligence mostly on google cloud services.

I've created documentation for architecture, external services and API services to make it easy to handover different parts of the projects. Also, transformed existing projects to test driven, and scalable codebase. Reducing technical debts and improving the codebase quality. In my free time, I'm also doing R&D and analysis to optimize cloud service usage.

Aug, 2019 - Aug, 2020

Alibaba.aero - Tehran, Iran

NodeJS Backend Developer - Full-time

I've worked as a back-end developer on the International and Domestic Hotel team.

- Implemented and aggregated over 10 inventory management softwares into the core service, resulting in delivering 25% cheaper rates to the customers.
- Built tools and services to make efficient integrations with the other departments including the billing and invoicing team which saved over 10 hours of monthly manual work.
- Created multiple microservices and enhanced the architecture of services.
- Created software to detect financial discrepancies, which reduced a lot of manual work and helped reduce account balance mismatches with 10% direct impact on the GMV.

Jun, 2019 - Aug, 2019

TripeMa - Tehran, Iran

NodeJS Backend Developer - Full-time

TripeMa was an accommodation startup that was acquired by Alibaba.aero. I joined them right before the acquisition and I was responsible to integrate their product with Alibaba's platform and enhance the back-end to fulfill product needs.

I've refactored 9 existing services including search and discovery, merchandising and financial services and communicated each step with the client team which included both mobile and front-end team members.

Feb, 2018 – Jun, 2019

## Serendip Agency

Full Stack Developer, Co-founder — Full-time

I have created a data dashboard, multiple services and NPM packages using MEAN stack, focusing on providing data browsing and visualizing tools for existing NoSQL databases.

github.com/serendip-archive

Jun, 2013 - Feb, 2018

## Self employed

Full Stack Developer — Freelance/Contract

I have worked for 5 years as a freelance developer in more than 30 small and mid-size projects with different companies. I've created softwares such as ERP, CRM, automation services, IOT backend services, time-sheet management, fund management, commercial websites, consultation services, and hybrid Cordova applications.

Nov, 2013 - Dec, 2014

Farzaneh Gostar - Tehran, Iran

.NET Backend Developer — Part-time

Farzaneh Gostar was a hosting and website development company.

I have developed several projects for them such as premium file sharing, account management, and worked on new website projects and maintaining the old ones.

# **EDUCATION**

SEP, 2012- MAY, 2014

Andishe - Tehran, Iran

Diploma at mathematics and physics

# PERSONAL PROJECTS

## E2DB - E2E encryption for your database and files

For the sake of security and privacy of users and their data. Services only need to have access to part of the user's data which they are granted access to while the remaining data should be only decrypted on user demand and E2DB provides this service.

npmjs.com/package/e2db github.com/e2db

#### Serendip Framework - Yet another Node.js web service framework written in typescript

The main goal for creating this framework was to have a shared package that could provide all frequently used services in a specific setting which was needed for speeding up the development of the rest of the Serendip platform repositories. It implements several RFC to provide authentication services, such as RFC 6749, RFC 6750, and RFC 6819

npmjs.com/serendip
github.com/serendip-framework

#### Multi Branch - Instance per branch of your node project repository

Did you ever want to run more than one branch of your code at a time? This personal project provides the ability to switch between multiple branches by simply setting an HTTP header key named 'branch'

npmjs.com/multi-branch github.com/node-multi-branch

# **GridDB** - Grid database using remote stand alone MongoDB instances.

It's a set of nodes and controllers communicating and syncing with each other by creating a grid of stand-alone MongoDB databases that are both secure and reliable in a condition you might want to switch between cloud and on-premises infrastructure.

github.com/serendip-griddb-provider

## WebSocket Cluster with NestJs and Redis (Article)

Scaling is an inevitable part of the back-end lifecycle and once you decide to scale your application to multiple instances, you are going to face a problem with handling users with multiple clients (phone, laptop, ...) each connecting to a random instance of your cluster.

medium.com/@mohsenes